After more than a century of de facto separation from the Chinese mainland by Japanese colonialism and U.S. intervention, Taiwan remains a rhetorical and military flashpoint of renewed Cold War aggression on China.

This selected timeline and resource compilation provides a deeper look into the forces that have produced “Taiwan independence” as a political consensus shared by U.S. politicians, erstwhile Western leftists, and Taiwan’s ruling Democratic Progressive Party. Amidst warmongering rhetoric fueled by Western claims of imminent Chinese invasion, this compilation serves as a starting point for understanding China’s aspirations for national reunification and Taiwan’s overdetermined status as an “unsinkable aircraft carrier” for Western ideological, economic, and military power in Asia and the Pacific.

Introduction

In the Western imagination, Taiwan exists as little more than a staging ground for ideological war with the People’s Republic of China—a crossroads of democracy versus authoritarianism, Western values versus Chinese backwardness, and free market capitalism versus closed-door communism. Yet for centuries, the island of Taiwan has played a rich and pivotal role in broader Chinese history. Located just one hundred miles from the mainland’s southeastern coast, Taiwan was linked to the mainland through migration, trade, language and culture long before European and Japanese colonizers seized on its strategic location as a launchpad for economic and military forays against China at large. Today, this history continues as U.S. imperialism positions Taiwan as an ideological and military base for its new Cold War against China.

Taiwan’s separation from the Chinese mainland began in 1895, when the Qing government was forced to cede Taiwan to Japan after its defeat in the First Sino-Japanese War. While Japan’s surrender at the end of World War II legally restored Chinese sovereignty over Taiwan, the Chinese civil war and the global Cold War once again rendered Taiwan an instrument for imperial ambitions against China. For the ascendant postwar United States, the 1949 establishment of the PRC under the Communist Party of China marked the “loss of China”—a blow that was partially recouped by propping up the fleeing Chiang Kai-shek government in Taiwan as “Free China.” In 1950, as the U.S. waged war to prevent the socialist unification of Korea, President Harry Truman dispatched the U.S. Navy’s Seventh Fleet to the Taiwan Strait to similarly foreclose the possibility of a unified socialist China. The legacy of that militarized division remains today, as the U.S. enforces the separation of Taiwan from the PRC through multibillion-dollar arms sales, menacing war games, and a concerted propaganda drive which together undermine the possibility of peaceful reunification. This bipartisan campaign of hybrid warfare has intensified over the last fifteen years, following China’s rise as a major power, the corresponding U.S. Pivot to Asia, and the era of “decoupling” pursued by both the Trump and Biden administrations. As the U.S. military declares the Pacific its primary theater of war, successive U.S. administrations have marshaled enormous economic, military, and ideological resources to build up Taiwan as a focal point for this new Cold War. This program violates the letter of the one-China principle and the spirit of the United States’ own “one-China policy,” which together have formed the basis for bilateral relations since 1979. Furthermore, they neglect the centuries-long shared history of Taiwan and its people with their neighbors across the strait.

Just as Western colonialism was once justified as a “civilizing mission,” U.S. imperial designs on Taiwan and China at large march under the banner of promoting “democracy” and defending the international “rules-based order.” The U.S. claim to be acting in defense of Taiwan’s “vibrant democracy” from Chinese authoritarianism is particularly ahistorical, given that the United States is responsible for propping up the Kuomintang (KMT) military dictatorship under Chiang and his successors for almost forty years. Meanwhile, despite grandiose language about U.S. global leadership, the reality is that the majority of the world understands cross-strait relations to be an internal matter for China. Only eleven UN member states maintain formal diplomatic relations with Taiwan (as the Republic of China), and no country recognizes Taiwan as an independent nation. This fact is unsurprising; UN recognition of the PRC as the legitimate representative of China came on the wings of overwhelming support from the Third World. Having experienced the genocidal violence and economic exploitation inherent to the Western imperial system, the Global South, like China itself, adheres to the tenets of sovereignty and non-interference.

Though ideologically diverse, proponents of Taiwan independence rely on an overlapping revisionist toolkit that elides the historical context of unresolved civil war shaping the cross-strait relationship. Instead, China’s aspirations for national unity are cast in terms of imperialism and expansionism. The era of KMT martial law is counterfactually invoked as precedent for authoritarian Chinese encroachment, obscuring the historical KMT-CPC rivalry and the role of the U.S. in supporting the military dictatorship. Meanwhile, the history of Japanese colonialism has been systematically revised to present a relatively “benign” rule that forms the bedrock for a non-Chinese local identity. Claims that Taiwan’s democracy has “voted out” reunification as a political pathway omit the crucial context that the island’s most vocal left-wing supporters of unification were systematically purged, jailed, and murdered under Japanese colonialism and KMT rule. Efforts to co-opt Taiwan’s yuánzhùmín, or indigenous peoples (see Notes on Terminology #3), into the project of Taiwan independence rely on a similar level of obfuscation; despite the separatist camp’s appropriation of decolonial rhetoric, yuánzhùmín have historically been apathetic towards the pro-independence Democratic Progressive Party (DPP). And in spite of attempts to stake Taiwan separatism to a schema of ethnic difference, official demographics list 95% of Taiwan’s population as being Han Chinese, the majority ethnic group of the Chinese mainland.

While those on the left may be (rightfully) skeptical of elite rhetoric of freedom and democracy, this rhetoric of Chinese imperialism, settler colonialism, and ethnic chauvinism may be harder to parse for those unfamiliar with Taiwan’s history. Yet, whether it is couched in the moralizing language of classic Cold Warriors or self-styled leftists, Taiwan independence ultimately serves the material interests of Western imperialism. Like the European and Japanese imperialists that colonized Taiwan for access to Chinese trade from the 17th through the 20th century, the United States transparently envisions the island as an outpost for efforts to contain China militarily and decouple from it economically. More than 70 years since U.S. military leader Douglas MacArthur described Taiwan as an “unsinkable aircraft carrier” in the nation’s Cold War against China, Taiwan remains a crude asset for U.S. military realpolitik. It is the linchpin of the so-called first island chain that links the 400 U.S. military bases spread across Asia and the Pacific and, crucially, home to Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Company, the world’s largest advanced semiconductor chip manufacturer. Lofty narratives of Taiwan independence thus ultimately fuel consent for militarization, intervention, and war while marginalizing anti-imperialist voices for diplomacy and peace. They also disguise the true intent of retaining Taiwan as a neocolonial outpost of Western empire to undermine China’s sovereign economic development. There is no “independence” in becoming a U.S. client regime entrapped in a capitalist world order. It would set a precedent for any country, large or small, that challenges U.S. hegemony to be balkanized with impunity. For the left to support such an outcome would be self-sabotage on an epic scale, regardless of the titanic politico-economic shifts on both sides of the strait since the Chinese Revolution of 1949.

The modern-day context around cross-strait relations is complex and evolving, and the lives of Chinese people on both sides of the Taiwan strait have been negatively affected by centuries of imperialism. We recognize that there is no perfect, clear-cut path to development after colonization and civil war, but insist on China’s right to defend its sovereign project of socialist construction. Cross-strait relations should be debated and resolved on Chinese terms and in Chinese dialogues only. They should not be used as crude ammunition in the U.S.-led geopolitical assault on China.

This syllabus includes a condensed timeline of Taiwan’s history to provide historical context to contemporary discussions about China, as well as a list of resources that highlight key aspects of cross-strait relations and history. It is not intended to be comprehensive in scope, for Taiwan’s place in Chinese history extends far beyond the recent centuries of Western and Japanese imperialism in Asia. Nor is it intended to offer simple answers to questions about mainland China and Taiwan. It aims only to be a starting point for critical inquiry, and we urge readers to seek a diversity of sources and form their own opinions. A more detailed understanding requires further study into Taiwan’s history, cross-strait relations, Chinese politics, and ongoing geopolitical developments.

a.

Pre-Colonial Taiwan and Early European Colonization

~15,000 years ago: Glaciation during the late Pleistocene Ice Age lowers sea levels in the Taiwan Strait, forming a prehistoric land bridge that physically connects the island to mainland Asia until ~10,000 years ago in the early Holocene. Some of the earliest historical evidence of human habitation in Taiwan comes from this period.

~4000 BCE: A new wave of seaborne migration to Taiwan begins, originating from what is today southeastern China. These people are known to have hunted, fished, performed horticulture, and cultivated rice and millet; they would become the ancestors of today’s yuánzhùmín.

Historical linguists believe Taiwan to be the origin of the Austronesian expansion. Through their common seafaring ancestors, yuánzhùmín are closely related to peoples that settled as far west as the Malagasy of Madagascar; to modern-day Filipinos, Malays, and Indonesians; and as far south and east as the Polynesians of Aotearoa / New Zealand, Hawai’i, and Easter Island.

As a result of these migrations, Taiwan became part of the Maritime Silk Road, a network of seabound trade routes spanning from China and Southeast Asia to India, the Arabian Peninsula, and the east coast of Africa.

Based on the island’s terrain, yuánzhùmín have long been differentiated into two broad groups. One group, inhabiting the western and northern plains, today includes the officially recognized Siraya, Makatao, and Taivoan peoples (along with many unrecognized groups). The other group, inhabiting the mountainous central and eastern highlands, today includes the officially recognized Amis, Atayal, Bunun, Kanakanavu, Kavalan, Paiwan, Puyuma, Rukai, Saaroa, Saisiyat, Sakizaya, Seediq, Taroko, Thao, Tsou, and Yami peoples.

The Chinese name Taiwan (臺灣 / 台湾) is thought to derive from that of the Taivoan people, who live near modern-day Tainan in the southwestern part of the island and were among the first to come in contact with both Chinese migrants and European colonists.

230 CE: Records from China’s Three Kingdoms period document an expedition from Eastern Wu that landed on an island referred to as “Yizhou” (夷洲). Most of its members are said to have died of unknown diseases, but the survivors brought back “several thousand” natives. Some historians have identified Yizhou with Taiwan.

607-610: The Book of Sui (the official history of the Sui Dynasty) records several expeditions to an island kingdom called “Liuqiu” (琉球) in the East China Sea. Modern historians identify it either as Taiwan or as the Ryukyus, an island chain to the northeast (currently governed by Japan) whose name is written with the same characters.

1171: Song Dynasty records document the presence of Chinese migrants on Penghu (澎湖), an archipelago just to the west of Taiwan (also known in Western literature as the Pescadores). Beginning that year, Song officials would send annual patrols and build permanent settlements to protect migrants from raids by peoples further to the east, most likely Taiwan or the Philippines.

1281: Penghu is incorporated into Jiangzhe province (comprising modern-day Fujian and Zhejiang) by the Yuan Dynasty.

1349: Chinese explorer Wang Dayuan (汪大淵) provides the first verified written account of Taiwan, documenting his interactions with yuánzhùmín and finding evidence (e.g. pottery) of prior contact but no permanent habitation by Chinese people.

1371: The newly founded Ming Dynasty institutes a ban on most maritime trade and coastal settlement, including a full withdrawal of Chinese settlers from Penghu. Defying the ban, Chinese merchants would continue traveling to Penghu and Taiwan and trading with the latter’s yuánzhùmín (with some learning their languages) in subsequent centuries.

1523: Ming China bans maritime trade with Japan specifically in hopes of stopping the increasing number of Japanese pirate attacks all along the Chinese coast. But the social and political upheaval in Japan during the Sengoku period only makes piracy more lucrative for Japanese and Chinese pirates alike. In particular, Lin Daoqian (林道乾) and Lin Feng (林鳳) would use Taiwan as a base for large-scale raids on the mainland in 1563 and 1574 respectively.

1542: Portuguese sailors on their way to Japan observe Taiwan and label it on their maps as Ilha Formosa (“beautiful island”), giving rise to the island’s standard name in most Western literature until the mid-20th century.

1593: Toyotomi Hideyoshi, chancellor and imperial regent of Japan, demands tribute from the “ruler of Taiwan” but finds no one of that description. This occurs just a year after he launched a massive invasion of Joseon Korea with the eventual aim of conquering Ming China as well – a confluence of events that in many ways presaged the First Sino-Japanese War almost exactly three centuries later.

Under the Tokugawa shogunate, Japan would launch failed invasions of Taiwan in 1609 and 1616 before adopting the isolationist sakoku policy in 1633, ending all interest in occupying the island for another two centuries.

1603: Chinese explorer Chen Di (陳第) visits Taiwan on an expedition to suppress Japanese pirates, writing a detailed account of the lives and customs of yuánzhùmín titled Dongfanji (東番記, lit. “Account of the Eastern Barbarians”).

1624: The Dutch East India Company builds Fort Zeelandia near modern-day Tainan, marking the beginning of formal European colonization on the island. The colony of Dutch Formosa in southwest Taiwan becomes a major entrepot for trade with China, Japan, and the East Indies, aiming to prevent competing European empires (mainly the Spanish and Portuguese) from establishing footholds in East Asia.

When the Dutch arrive, they find several thousand Chinese residents already present on the island. Under their rule, tens of thousands more migrants would be recruited or kidnapped from Fujian province and brought to Taiwan as agricultural laborers, raising the total Han population to around 40,000. The Dutch would also attempt to forcibly convert large numbers of yuánzhùmín to Christianity, meeting stiff resistance (especially from the Siraya) that would not be quelled until 1636.

1628: The Spanish Empire attempts to start another colony in northern Taiwan with the building of Fort Santo Domingo. Compared to the Dutch, they are much less successful in this effort. In 1642, they would destroy the fort themselves after the Dutch defeat them in the Second Battle of San Salvador and expel them from the island.

1644: The Ming Dynasty loses its capital Beijing, and shortly thereafter most of mainland China, to the Manchu-led Qing Dynasty. Some Ming loyalists retreat to Xiamen in Fujian province and continue resisting the Qing for several decades under the leadership of general Zheng Chenggong (鄭成功), also known in the West as Koxinga.

1652: Under the leadership of Guo Huaiyi (郭懷一), Han Chinese peasants in Taiwan launch a large-scale revolt against colonial rule that is suppressed by the Dutch and some of their yuánzhùmín allies. The peasants’ main grievance is a colonial head tax applied to Chinese but not yuánzhùmín. Around 4000 migrants or 10% of the island’s Han population are killed; one historian considers this “the first Chinese antiwestern uprising in modern history.”

1662: From his base in Xiamen, Zheng Chenggong leads an army that joins forces with both Han migrants and yuánzhùmín (whom he persuaded to turn on their erstwhile allies) and successfully expels the Dutch from Taiwan and Penghu. There he establishes the Kingdom of Tungning (東寧國) with the aim of restoring the Ming Dynasty in alliance with other loyalist strongholds in the south of mainland China. He dies shortly after and is succeeded by his son Zheng Jing (鄭經). At its height, the kingdom would control maritime routes between the East and South China Seas and maintain a trade network spanning from Japan and Korea to Southeast Asia.

In order to starve out the Tungning Kingdom, the Qing Dynasty issued its own ban on maritime trade and coastal settlement in Guangdong, Fujian, Zhejiang, Jiangsu, even as far north as Shandong province – often as far as 25 kilometers inland. With Dutch help, Qing forces finally managed to capture Xiamen and the other Ming loyalist bases on the mainland by 1663 (though Zheng Jing would briefly retake them during the 1673-81 Revolt of the Three Feudatories). Ironically this “Great Clearance” policy had the effect of triggering another wave of migration to Taiwan, bringing its Han population to at least 100,000.

Zheng Chenggong is widely revered today on both sides of the Taiwan Strait, but for markedly different reasons. In the mainland he is regarded as a hero for liberating Taiwan from Dutch colonial rule and thereby inflicting the first major defeat of a Western imperial power at Chinese hands. In Taiwan on the other hand, the Ming loyalist Kingdom of Tungning is seen by Kuomintang supporters as a forerunner of the post-1949 Republic of China (with the PRC playing an analogous role to the Qing Dynasty), and rather ahistorically by independence supporters as a specifically “Taiwanese” proto-state.

1683: Qing forces under the command of Admiral Shi Lang (施琅), a former Zheng loyalist, take advantage of political turmoil after the death of Zheng Jing to mount an invasion of Penghu and Taiwan. They force the Kingdom of Tungning to surrender, putting an end to the last major outpost of Ming restorationism. (Small pockets of Ming loyalist resistance would sporadically arise for another century or so.) The length and severity of the conflict underscored Taiwan’s strategic location and importance as a base for foreign and domestic attacks on mainland China.

1684 May: The Qing Dynasty incorporates Taiwan as a prefecture of Fujian province, located right across the strait from the island.

During the next two centuries, the population of Taiwan grew to around three million as the rice, sugar, and fishing industries expanded. Significant numbers of Chinese merchants and laborers would also migrate seasonally between Taiwan and their home villages on the mainland, cultivating cross-strait trade without necessarily settling permanently.

Qing authorities generally placed high importance on maintaining order and preventing conflict between Chinese migrants and yuánzhùmín. Early on they repatriated many soldiers and refugees who had left the mainland for Taiwan during the war. They also imposed a permit system to restrict migration from the mainland (especially of full families), though it was often ignored by local officials and would be fully lifted in 1875. Most notably, from 1739-1875 Chinese migrants were banned from entering or acquiring land in the mountains of central and eastern Taiwan; during that period no uprisings by highland yuánzhùmín were recorded. On the other hand the lowland yuánzhùmín were largely sinicized and/or assimilated into Han culture, often through intermarriage when only single Chinese men were allowed to migrate.

That said, intra-ethnic tensions among Han Taiwanese erupted into violence so often that they inspired the phrase “三年一小反, 五年一大乱” (lit. “every three years a minor uprising, every five years a major rebellion”). Many migrants tended to identify with their original hometowns, religious sects, or language groups and were suspicious of those from different locales. When they arrived, they brought with them clan feuds and other rivalries from the Chinese mainland. Residual Ming loyalist sentiment also contributed to the unrest, most notably in the large-scale rebellions of Zhu Yigui (朱一貴) in 1721 and Lin Shuangwen (林爽文) in 1786. Yuánzhùmín often served as reliable allies and auxiliaries of the Qing government during such intra-ethnic conflict.

Appendix

Notes on Terminology

Since 1949 the de facto governing authority over the islands of Taiwan, Penghu, Kinmen, and Matsu has retained the official name “Republic of China” (中華民國), or ROC for short. For the sake of clarity and consistency we adhere to this usage throughout the timeline. However, this does not imply recognition of the ROC's claim to legitimacy as a continuation of the pre-1949 government of both mainland China and Taiwan. Official statements from PRC officials and media typically refer to the “Taiwan authorities” (台湾当局), while the pro-independence camp and mainstream Western media usually refer to this de facto state entity simply as “Taiwan” – leading to ahistorical and incorrect formulations like “president of Taiwan,” “flag of Taiwan,” etc. In non-governmental contexts we use the common demonym “Taiwanese” for people residing and/or born and raised in Taiwan, and for entities based there.

The political divide between mainland China and Taiwan is also reflected in different writing and romanization systems for the Chinese language. The PRC has used simplified Chinese characters since the 1960s, while Taiwan continues to use traditional characters. With romanization the situation is arguably even more complicated: Hanyu Pinyin (汉语拼音) has been the standard in mainland China since 1958 (and internationally since 1982), while Taiwan has never adopted a standard romanization system. In this timeline and resource list we use pinyin to romanize names of mainland Chinese places and individuals predominantly associated with mainland China after 1949, as well as all pre-1949 Chinese individuals with some exceptions for persons commonly known in English under non-standard romanizations (e.g. Sun Yat-sen, Chiang Kai-shek). For places under de facto ROC jurisdiction and post-1949 Taiwanese individuals, we default to the most common romanizations of their names in English-language media. When each person is first mentioned we also include their Chinese name in parentheses: in simplified characters for post-1949 mainland individuals, and in traditional characters for post-1949 Taiwanese individuals as well as all pre-1949 Chinese individuals.

The term běnshěngrén (本省人, lit. “people of this province”) refers to Chinese people in Taiwan whose ancestors, predominantly Hoklo (福佬) and Hakka (客家) from Fujian and Guangdong provinces, migrated to the island before the end of Japanese colonization in 1945. The term wàishěngrén (外省人, lit. “people from outside the province”) refers to those who moved to Taiwan from the mainland after 1945, as well as their descendants. Běnshěngrén do not include the non-Han peoples whose presence in Taiwan predates Chinese migration; those people are the Taiwanese yuánzhùmín (台湾原住民, lit. “original peoples of Taiwan”). Yuánzhùmín is typically translated into English as “aboriginal” or “indigenous,” both of which can imply a colonial relationality whose applicability in Taiwan is a matter of active debate. We therefore choose to leave the term untranslated, in analogy with wàishěngrén and běnshěngrén, so as to clearly delineate the island’s original inhabitants from those běnshěngrén who (especially in the pro-independence camp) have increasingly taken to describing themselves as "native Taiwanese."